Tracking team, report on both units' current positions.
Pod 02-Dash has achieved operational altitude.
It has settled into the targeted orbit.
Pod 08 was unable to breach target orbital range due to insufficient altitude.
Copy that.
02-Dash will conduct a solo operation.
Roger.
Pod 08 will act as support.
Transition shift to 7.
Pod 02-Dash is beyond the point of recovery.
Breaching Area 88.
Roger.
Commence Operation US.
Pod 02-Dash will enter the final operational orbit.
Deceleration in progress.
Stage 1, ignite all engines.
Combustion imminent.
S1C combustion complete.
Deceleration confirmed.
Jettisoning booster unit, stage 1.
Separation confirmed.
Combustion systems cleared. No problems detected.
Roger.
Automating ignition timing.
Igniting all engines, stage 2.
S1C combustion complete.
Closing pressure valves.
Jettisoning booster unit, stage 2.
Deceleration complete.
Preparing to enter final operational orbit.
Flipping unit head.
Commencing rotation.
Descent angle confirmed.
Within an acceptable margin of error.
Recalculating relative velocity.
Reconfirming coordinate altitude.
No problems.
Final orbit corrections complete.
180-degree rotation complete.
Roger.
Pod 02-Dash will transition to the intersection orbit.
Now commencing the operation.
All remote guiding will now be cut.
Unit will be controlled manually.
Good luck.
Unit is on course to intersect with the target.
Eight miles remaining until contact.
Confirming target.
Contact point is unchanged.
Maintaining Shift-M. No problems.
02-Dash, prepare to rendezvous.
08 is lacking altitude, so it can only assist you in the 96 seconds until re-entry.
Finish this by then.
Reflective waves detected in target space.
It's jamming us!
It's just the auto-defense system's mass weapon.
No need to worry.
Burst flows generated!
Incoming in 3... 2... 1...
Second wave incoming.
Blood type: blue.
They're a pesky bunch.
Identifying approaching body...
Confirmed to be Mk. 04A.
An Anti-A.T. Field!
This sucks!
It's just getting in my way!
Hey, Glasses! Some backup here!
Support fire was two seconds late!
And you're three seconds ahead of position.
It's called adapting to the situation. Keep up with me!
As you command,
Princess!
It got through the Fraury Shift.
It'll break into Final Defense Area 89.
The target is moving!
No time to correct my orbit!
I'm going in!
Decelerate!
Eight!
Seven!
Six!
Five!
Four!
Three!
Two!
One!
Terminating combustion!
02-Dash has jettisoned the last boosters.
Ensuring safe distance for re-entry.
Successfully seized the target.
Returning to base.
Roger.
We'll be waiting at the retrieval point.
The join code is Saturn 5.
Roger.
Blood type blue?
Where?!
The triggering object is Mk. 04B.
It is deploying indo-hashamas.
The nerve!
Right before re-entry, too.
Glasses, back-up!
Sorry!
I don't have enough altitude, so see ya!
I'll leave the rest to y-...
Ugh! She's useless!
Damn, this thing is stubborn!
Nobody told me about this!
What's with this light?!
The A.T. Field isn't neutralizing it!
I can't get at the core block!
You're not getting away!
Crap! I can't maintain my descent angle!
My unit will break apart at this rate!
02-Dash, completing the mission takes top priority!
Don't let go of the target object, even if it means sacrificing the unit.
I already know that!
Do something, you idiot, Shinji!
Welcome home, Ikari Shinji-kun.
I've been waiting for you.
Cardiopulmonary function is nominal.
No discernible paralysis of the extremities.
Yes. His eyes are opening.
Can you understand me?
What is this place?
He's responsive.
He seems to have returned to a conscious state.
Really, we have to help Ayanami.
Yes, continuity of memory also seems acceptable.
Um, where's Ayanami...?
Is this someone you know?
It's... me.
He is capable of self-recognition as well.
There seems to be no problem.
What's this?
Installation list for refill operations cleared up to 86%.
Online N2 reactor maintaining output of 90%.
No ships visible within a perimeter of 1200.
No unidentified flying objects can be confirmed, either.
Prioritize ships in the D block for the transferral of crew.
/ We don't have enough personnel for the transfer operation!
/ #####??????
Checking the roadmap for the camouflage operation.
Specimen BM03 is in our custody.
Understood.
Release the restraints.
You can step down.
Misato-san...
It is Ikari Shinji-kun, isn't it?
So it would seem.
His physical data is identical to Code Third Boy.
/ Post birth dental treatment scars and body composition are reproduced perfectly by(?) Near Surge.
We are now analyzing his deep level sync test results.
And the application of the DSS Choker?
Its installation has already been arranged, Captain Katsuragi.
Captain Katsuragi...?
It is you after all!
Activation nominal.
Passcode is set exclusive to the Captain.
Understood.
What is this thing?!
Please, take it off already!
That's never going to be taken off.
Interview complete.
Take him to quarantine.
Decoys 01 and 05 destroyed.
Insufficiency in wave's length.
The hell's this?
It's Pattern Blue.
Target identified.
Mk. 4C.
It's the Nemesis Series.
They're back...
Targets are all Mk. 4C.
They're advancing on all sides.
They intend to cordon us here, to start with.
/ ???02(???)????06(????)??????
We can't afford to move from here yet.
Continue only with main engine's operations.
All fleets to Second Battle Stations.
Target: All Nemesis Series.
Roger.
All fleets to Second Battle Stations.
Prepare for anti-air, anti-water, and underwater battle.
Abandon stock transfer.
Prioritize the transferring of all personnel to another vessel.
All fleets, abandoning stock transfer.
All personnel, transferring vessels is top priority!
All aircraft are to withdraw from our current air space.
Hurry to Meeting Point 2.
Abandon any leftover cargo.
Migration of crew takes top priority.
/ ????????????????????????
/ ??????????####?????
Prepare all cannons to shoot.
Remote control and interlock systems, activating.
/ #######
Initiate main power system injection.
Hurry.
N2 reactor operating at 99%.
Initiating main power system injection.
Opening valves up to number 90.
Transmission pipe connected.
No problems detected in the port, and 3rd and 4th cargo cage.
Roger.
Opening all valves up to 90.
Begin energy injection.
Injecting power to N2 reactor.
All nominal.
Verifying the interior of the LCL tube.
Filtration system is go.
Battle stations!
Get back to your departments.
You there! No idling!
You're asking for the impossible, Ma'am!
We are something of a mixed group with civilians amongst us, after all.
No excuses!
Get to work!
Ugh, this is why I can't stand younger men.
Umm... interrupting the transfer here.
Commencing lockdown of barrier walls... is this it?
The sonar is in this direction with the bow of the anti-air ship as reference.
Kitakami!
What's the status of the procedures on deck?
Am I in charge of that?
That's your post! Of course!
Whaat? For real?
The start-up is dangerous.
Let's stay here!
Preparations for all anti-air defenses concluded, including the guided missiles of the battle ship.
Having battle stations on the bridge...
Roger.
It's so nerve-wracking!
Activate all anti-air systems.
Safeguarding Eva-01 is our number-one priority.
...Eva-01?
It's here!
Confirming the target's pillar of light.
Its... numbers are increasing somehow!
We can't grasp the target's core block.
It is probably being concealed on the outside of a phased cocoon.
This is bad.
At this rate, we'll be on the receiving end of a saturation bombing.
600 seconds until contact.
Captain Katsuragi,
I propose an immediate dispersal of the fleets.
We have insufficient crew and limited resources.
Compounding the problem, this main ship's camouflage equipment is incomplete.
On top of that, we cannot attack to capture the target's core blocks.
In other words, our chance of winning is zero.
At this point, we should retreat like we usually do.
There is no way.
Captain Katsuragi!
This is why I will change the current situation to neutralize any possibly anxiety.
Vice Captain, we're going to fly.
Fly?!
You can't be thinking of using the main ship?
All hands, prepare for launch!
Prepare for ignition of the main engines!
It's too reckless to use the main ship all of a sudden, Captain Katsuragi!
I agree!
We haven't even run a test flight. It's too dangerous.
Anti-gravity also hasn't been tested.
I don't have confidence in it.
I don't want to fight battles that can't be won.
I don't want to die just yet.
You die when you die. That's all there is to it.
Quit your whining, kids.
/ Wah... Old folks should be more careful!
I am aware of the recklessness.
We will use this ship as decoy and fish them out to the surface!
The power to kill gods. I will see it through to the end.
But the most important ignition system has not been installed.
Don't tell me you're going to use the Evas?
Mari!
Eva-08 isn't ready yet.
Asuka!
...Asuka?
I'm already on it!
I just have to shove the ignition engine in, right?
I'm counting on you.
But there is a problem with the barrier density around the ship.
Plus, isn't there work being done on the bridge?
Well, "prioritize the objective, human life expendable" is a captain's motto, after all.
I'm going all out!
Eva Unit 02', activate!
Eva-02' is launching.
Roger.
Preparing Eva-02' for launch.
Underwater motor and jet propulsion, passing through number 1.
Really, such a boring entrance for my unit's new looks.
It really is Eva-02.
Thank god. Asuka is okay.
Misato, I...
All fleets to Primary Battle Stations.
Repeat, all fleets to Primary Battle Stations.
Changing battle command system.
Main crew, to the main bridge.
Prepare gravity ballast.
Roger.
All vents, check.
Centralize the ship's primary controls in the anchor lead plug.
Roger.
Prepare for descent.
Inductor, confirmed.
Entering countdown.
Misato-san!
Eva-01 is here, isn't it?
I'll pilot too!
I'll help Asuka!
You don't need me to pilot Eva-01?
Misato-san?!
That's correct.
There's no need for you to pilot the Eva.
/ ###???????
Command system is currently being transferred to the battle ship bridge.
Repeat, command system is currently being transferred to the battle ship bridge.
No need?
Then... what should I do?
Misato-san!
Ikari Shinji-kun...
From now on, do nothing.
LCL being filled with gas.
Electrification density cleared.
Begin entry.
Status of LCL electric charge is nominal.
Starting all integrated operating systems.
What's our status?
Roll-call of all personnel is complete.
All confirmed on board.
First list cleared.
Closure of all barrier walls confirmed.
Terminating pressure resistance check.
Output of auxiliary components is currently climbing.
Injecting power for initial system activation.
5% until it hits critical.
Initiating gyro-compass.
Stabilizer nominal.
Commencing visual data processing.
Turning on the main monitor.
Target is still closing in.
Currently taking on an encircling formation.
Eva-02' deploying propellors.
Left arm is being switched out.
Here we go!
Well then!
Let's do it!
Spreading A.T. Field.
They changed into pillars of light.
Their energy is rocketing!
All targets are starting to move.
Ally ships have been evaporated!
It's a saturation attack.
If this ship gets caught too, it's all over.
Another 360 seconds until contact!
Here we go!
Eva-02' has commenced operations.
/ ######300%!
No matter!
Transfer all energy to the flywheel!
Give that top priority!
/ ?80###????##?????!
Converter Group No. 7 has exploded!
Disregard the downed lines!
Continue the forced injection!
Ignore all pressure meters!
Releasing the lock on the flywheel crimp.
Beginning rotation!
Initiating main energy pump.
Auxiliary component output has reached 80%.
Force insert the catalyst!
So now there's...
39 seconds remaining!
Rotational speed currently climbing!
Eva-02' maintaining critical pressure.
We're there!
Fly wheel charged to 102%, over critical!
We're in the final stage of activation.
Roger.
Switch to flight controls.
Starting ground to air regulation.
Transferring to 3D-type steering.
Deploy the A.T. Field at the same time we fire up.
Rotation rate 36000. All green.
Coming into contact!
Omit countdown.
Main contact.
Contact!
Ignite!
Obstacles cleared.
Confirming all divisions.
/ 16?###?
Consort ships have all retreated.
Here we go.
Wunder, launch!
Main wings penetrated! Damage unknown!
Don't sweat it!
Prepare for a full-scale counterattack.
Upend the ship!
Go astern!
Go astern! Forward, ho!
Pull out the remains of the core blocks from the phased cocoon.
Cracks have been sustained on the ends of the main wings!
Keep the rudder steady!
Run main engines at full power!
Both sides at maximum!
Full throttle!
The core blocks are out!
Now!
Port full power!
Swing it around!
Roger!
Thrusters at full power!
Crash stop!
Target is silent!
All cannons prepare to fire!
Load energy penetrating ammunition.
Connect all cannons to main ship.
Open ammunition supplying circuits!
Roger. Opening circuits.
Applying final corrections to computed enemy trajectories!
Artillery systems are interlocked.
Direct aim and manual pursuit, good to go on all cannons.
Then we're all set.
FIRE!
Target destroyed!
All fleets, go to secondary state of alert.
Prepare to retrieve Eva-02'.
Hurry with emergency procedures for the main wings.
Amazing!
We really won.
How totally reckless.
Well, she's an even more interesting captain than Kaji said.
So this is the power to kill gods.
Wunder really is the ship of hope.
Specimen BM03, Tentative Name Ikari Shinji-san...
The executive officer will have a word with you.
This is Eva-01...?
Yes. Eva-01 is being used as the main engine of this ship.
Consequently, you serve no function as a pilot.
Ah, so I really am not needed.
Also, your sync test results have come back.
The sync rate is 0.00%.
Even if you were to get in the Eva, it wouldn't activate.
Really?
Isn't that great news, Ikari-san?
Even so, we cannot overlook the fact that, earlier, Eva-01 suddenly entered an Awakened state for 12 seconds.
As a result, the DSS Choker has been installed on you.
What is this?
Safety for us.
It's a physical safety device to circumvent Awakenings.
And it is also a symbol of your punishment.
What does it do?
If you lose control of your emotions while piloting an Eva and become unable to suppress the risk of Awakening,
this will intervene by terminating your life.
Does that mean... I will die?
I will not deny that.
No way...
Misato-san, what is all this about dying?
This is weird, Misato-san!
Suddenly it's all so confusing, and I don't understand anything!
It can't be helped that you're confused.
Second Lieutenant!
Yes, ma'am!
Introduce yourself.
Um, it's late, but I'm the medical officer in charge,
2nd Lt. Suzuhara Sakura.
Nice to meet you.
Ah, s-same.
But, "Suzuhara"...
Are you Toji's...?
Ah, yes.
I owe everything to my big brother.
I'm his little sister Sakura.
Little sister?
Don't you mean big sister?
No, little sister.
Little sister...? How?
Fourteen years have passed since then.
Stupid Shinji.
Huh? Ah, Asuka!
Thank god.
You really are safe, Asuka!
I can't stand it.
I've been holding this in.
What was that all about...?
Built up anger and grief.
What do you mean...?
Uh, Asuka, your left eye...
None of your business.
Asuka, you said it's been fourteen years,
but the only thing that's changed about you is that eyepatch.
Right. It's the Curse of Eva.
A curse?
Wait!
Asuka, maybe you know!
Where's Ayanami?!
Dunno.
You don't know...?
But I saved her!
All this fuss over just one person.
This world doesn't have time to cater to your ego.
Isn't that right, Captain Katsuragi?
Asuka!
Misato-san, where's Ayanami?!
You've got to tell me!
Shinji-kun, Ayanami Rei no longer exists.
No, I saved her, I know I did.
She must still be in Eva-01's plug.
Please, search for her!
We've already conducted a thorough sweep of Eva-01.
We only found you.
And for some reason, this was restored.
The inspection yielded no problems. We'll return it.
My father's...
Ayanami was holding it then.
So I saved her, didn't I?
What?!
It's me.
Target is on the rear deck!
It suddenly closed in on us!
So the champion is on the scene...
All fleets to Primary Battle Stations.
Safeguarding Eva-01 is top priority!
Eva-08, you're ready to go, right?
But of course.
I'm right on top of it, Princess.
By the way, how was Puppy Boy?
Is he obediently staying put?
Nothing's changed about his stupid lowly face.
Oh, so you went to go see his face, did you?
No!
I just threw a punch at him!
I feel much better now.
Misato-san, Ritsuko-san!
Just who is coming?
Is it a new Angel?!
Ikari-kun, where are you?
Ayanami?
That was Ayanami's voice just now, wasn't it?!
Misa-
What is going on here?!
Preparations complete!
Ikari-san, this way!
Ikari-kun, where are you?
It really is Ayanami.
It's Ayanami!
Ikari-san! Quickly!
Enough.
Ayanami, I'm right here!
Eva... Unit 00.
Ikari-kun...
Come this way.
Don't do it, Shinji-kun.
Just stay right here.
What's with that, Misato-san?
Weren't you just saying a moment ago that you didn't need me?
Even so, you'll be kept in our custody.
That's just too one-sided!
Please stop it!
That's why.
We will eradicate all of Nerv's Evas.
Nerv...
This isn't Nerv, too?
We are Wille, an organization dedicated to Nerv's annihilation.
That's...
No, but it's being piloted by Ayanami!
It's not her!
Rei is gone, Shinji-kun.
Liar!
I mean, she's right here, isn't she?!
You're just daft, Misato-san!
I've had enough!
Ikari-san!
It's okay if you go back, but...
Please, whatever you do, don't pilot an Eva!
We really could use a break...
Glasses, don't let it get away!
Loud and clear!
? When you take aim ?
? Be careful not to miss your mark ?
Hey, come on!
Got ya!
I knew it! An Adams' vessel?
At least say "hi" or something!
The fact he was taken in priority over Eva-01
means he still has potential as a trigger!
Misato! Use the DSS Choker!
Mission directive from Executive Officer.
Pursuit unnecessary.
All personnel, resume emergency damage control and camouflage operations.
Roger.
Pursuit unnecessary.
Hmph.
All personnel, resume emergency damage control and camouflage operations.
What do you know.
He's not an idiot, just a brat!
Evangelion New Theatrical Edition: Q
I did save her after all.
Misato-san lied to me.
This way.
Um...
Even though this is the Geofront, you can see the sky.
Is that... Nerv Headquarters?
What happened?
It really has been fourteen years.
Here.
What's this?
An Eva...?
That's right.
Father...
Evangelion 13.
A unit for you and that pilot.
The one on the piano earlier...
When the time comes, pilot this Eva along with the boy.
We are done talking.
Wait a second, Father!
I still have a lot of questions, a lot I want to talk about!
Father!
There's no dial tone,
so I can't reach anyone from here.
After all, I must thank her.
Ayanami!
Ayanami, where are you?
What is this place?
Ayanami?!
There you are!
Ayanami!
I've been looking for you!
Um. Ah, wait!
Clothes! Put some clothes on!
If that is an order, I will do it.
I'm coming in...
Um, Ayanami, thank you for this.
You got a new plugsuit.
It suits you. Though black is a little...
Nerv HQ has really changed a lot, hasn't it?
Why is Misato-san fighting against Nerv and not the Angels?
What does Father intend to do here?
What's happened to everyone?
Hey, Ayanami, do you know anything?
I do not.
I see...
/Yeah, you may be right.
Say, when did you return from Eva-01?
This place isn't much of a room.
You could say it's just your style,
but it doesn't seem like there is school, so what do you do all the time?
Wait. For orders.
There are no books here.
You're not reading any books?
Books?
If I were Ayanami Rei, would I read books?
Yeah. You read a lot, didn't you?
There were books in your room, too.
I see...
I got it!
I'll go look in the library here and bring you some.
Um, English books are good, right?
You always had one on you, so I guess you liked them.
"Liked"...?
Yeah... At least, I think so.
What is "liked"?
So Seele are still maintaining their silence?
The Human Instrumentality Project will be carried out according to the Dead Sea Scrolls.
We no longer need to weave the story.
Ikari, you intend to use Eva-13 this time?
No matter. I will go along with your plan.
For Yui-kun's sake.
It's no use. It doesn't work.
Do nothing.
None of your business.
Please, just don't pilot an Eva!
Pilot the Eva.
I don't know.
Come down here, Ikari-kun.
Let's talk!
Uh, aren't we going to talk?
A piano duet is a dialogue of sounds, you could say.
Why don't we try it?
No, that's alright. I can't play.
If you want to live well, you have to change and try new things.
Look, it's easy.
You just have to hit this key here.
Now, follow along with me.
Very good!
You're playing so well.
Every note is a joy.
We're amazing together, aren't we?
Thanks.
Same here.
We'll have to do this again.
You can come anytime, Ikari Shinji-kun.
Sure.
Oh, you are...?
I'm Kaworu, Nagisa Kaworu.
I'm a child chosen by fate, the same as you.
She's not here this time, either.
The books haven't been touched, either.
Good morning, Ikari Shinji-kun.
You're here early today.
I don't really have anything else to do.
It's been ages since I've had this much fun.
I wonder how I could play better...
You don't need to be good at playing it.
Just producing a pleasing sound will suffice.
So if I want to improve the sound I'm making, what should I do?
It takes repeated practice.
Doing it over and over, until it feels good enough to you.
We could watch the stars from here.
That's the only way.
It's okay, leave it to me.
You just need it to work, right?
Yeah. Thank you.
I feel bad for making you do so much for me.
You don't need to worry about that.
We're friends, after all.
It's gotten quite dark, hasn't it?
Why don't we head back for today?
Hey, why don't we stay here for a little longer?
The stars?
Do you like the stars?
Yeah.
It's always struck me how large the universe is.
There's something about it that's put my mind completely at ease, ever since I was little.
I guess I'm glad that it hasn't changed at all these past fourteen years.
Or maybe it makes me feel marginalized, but in a good way, if that makes sense.
Uh, it's hard to put into words.
Your feelings came through.
Instead of seeking change, you prefer a world of nothingness and brutal abyss.
It's like you.
Lying here together is nice.
I didn't know it could be so pleasant.
Thanks for inviting me.
No, you don't need to.
I just thought that it'd be fun, if you wanted to try it, and...
It is fun.
I really was born to meet you.
Hm?
Seems a little big this time.
Huh?
Suzuhara Toji
Here, it should work now.
Thanks.
You're amazing, Nagisa-kun.
You can do everything.
This is just knowledge.
It's because I've stayed in this world for a little longer than you.
Still... you're incredible.
You don't look too well.
What's wrong?
I'm worried about my friends.
Friends?
Yeah.
There was a city above Nerv HQ.
That's where everyone lived.
Toji, Kensuke,
Prez, the rest of the class...
Apparently I'd been sleeping in Eva-01 for fourteen years.
I don't know what's changed in that time.
Not knowing the answer to that must be painful.
Somehow, I'm scared.
Of what's happened to the city and everybody...
I'm scared of it for some reason.
That's right, I'm scared!
Do you want to know?
Nagisa-kun?
Nagisa-kun!
Just a little longer now.
The clouds will disperse soon,
and you will see the truth you desire.
What is this...?
The outcome of Third Impact, which came to pass while you were merged with Eva-01.
But this is...
The target is an Eva!
What happened to everyone in the city?
Mass extinction is not unusual on this planet.
Rather, it is the aspect that drives evolution.
Because life is fundamentally something that adjusts to the world and changes itself.
However, Lilin do not change themselves, but the world.
So they brought the rite of artificial evolution unto themselves.
Old life is offered in sacrifice,
so that new beings blessed with the Fruit of Life may be created.
All this is due to the death instinct that's been programmed since time immemorial.
Nerv call it the Human Instrumentality Project.
This is Nerv's...
This is what my father was doing.
Ikari Shinji-kun,
once Awakened, Eva-01 opened the Door of Guf
and became the trigger for Third Impact.
Lilin call it Near Third Impact.
It was all initiated by you.
You're wrong!
All I did was save Ayanami!
True, but that was the catalyst...
All this...
I didn't know!
You're telling me all of this so fast,
and there's nothing I can do about it!
Indeed.
There's nothing you can do about your past.
The truth you desired to know.
The Lilin are providing you reparation for your sin as a result.
That's what your neck device is, no?
What sin?
I didn't do anything!
I had nothing to do with it!
If it wasn't you, then who was it?
However, no sin is beyond redemption.
There is always hope.
Always.
Seele's boy has contacted the Third Boy.
He showed him the conditions outside, it seems.
Was his reaction as you anticipated?
Are you okay with all of this, Ikari?
Seele's scenario is being rewritten by us.
All existence is nothing more than a tool to that end.
You assume that your son wouldn't benefit even from seeing how you live?
I don't agree with that.
What is...
What am I supposed--
Right... I saved Ayanami.
Wasn't that the right thing?
She's gone again.
She still hasn't touched the books.
What's going on...?
What's wrong with Ayanami?!
Third Boy, do you play shogi?
Eh... I only sort of know the rules.
That's fine. Choose a side.
I'll start without a castle, bishop, and golden general.
Let your mind be still.
It's the only way to achieve victory.
You'll lose in another thirty-one turns.
Hmm...
Is it more fun for you this way?
Thank you for indulging an old man his hobby.
I'm a coward too, you know.
I used this game as a pretext to talk to you.
Do you remember your mother?
No. I was too small.
Father got rid of everything that was hers.
Is this...
Ayanami?
Your mother.
Maiden name, Ayanami Yui.
She was my student at the university.
Now, she is the control system of Eva Unit 01.
Hm. The power was finally restored.
The control system from very early in the Evas' development.
Here, Yui-kun proposed direct entry into cores,
and tested it with herself as the experimentee.
You were watching, too. Your memory must have been erased.
The result was that Yui-kun vanished here,
and only her data was recovered, in the Ayanami Series.
The Rei you know is one of Yui-kun's clones.
She is preserved within Eva-01, the same as your mother.
All of it is Ikari's plan.
No way...
Breaking the world is not difficult.
But rebuilding it, that isn't so easy.
The world can be reversed no more than time.
Nor even the human heart...
And thus, so that his wish might be granted,
Ikari is paying every price there is.
Even his very soul.
I've imparted to you a little of the truth.
About your father, as well...
I've been wanting to thank you for a while.
I could have been given a more pleasant part to play.
Yui-kun, this should do.
The time of the final contract is upon us.
We shall meet soon, Yui.
Why aren't you reading the books?
That wasn't your order.
"Order"...?
Alright, that's enough!
Are you still Ayanami...?
Yes, Ayanami Rei.
Then I did save you, right...?
...I don't know.
Ikari-kun...?
So, I didn't actually save her...
Ayanami...
Do nothing.
I don't know.
None of your business.
Pilot the Eva.
Whatever you do, don't pilot an Eva!
Do nothing.
None of your business.
Pilot the Eva.
Whatever you do, don't pilot an Eva!
Father...
I don't know.
Do nothing.
Pilot the Eva.
None of your business.
Whatever you do, don't pilot an Eva!
Do nothing.
Pilot the Eva.
None of your business.
Do nothing.
I don't know.
None of your business.
Pilot the Eva.
Do nothing.
I don't know.
...your business.
None of your business.
Whatever you do, don't pilot an Eva!
I don't know.
Pilot the Eva.
What did I do?
Has the final executor been completed?
Yes, everything we need is right here.
The time has come.
This is it, Ikari Shinji-kun.
No!
I don't want to pilot an Eva anymore!
I didn't save Ayanami after all!
Nothing good came out of me piloting the Eva!
I've had enough! I don't want to do anything!
And so, the refrain of bitter memories will keep good things from happening.
Nothing is ever good!
You were the one who showed me that, Kaworu.
A world where I can't do anything!
That which was changed by Eva can be changed back by Eva in turn.
You say that, but my father, Eva, Misato-san...
I can't believe in anyone, or anything!
Still, I want you to believe in me.
I can't!
Misato-san had this thing put on me!
They said to never pilot Eva again.
They said if I pilot, I'll die.
I don't care about Eva anymore.
I understand.
I will shoulder the burden of the Lilin's curse, and the risk of Eva's Awakening, for you.
Nagisa-kun...
You don't have to worry.
Because I was originally something created by the very Lilin who fear me.
I had intended to do this at some point.
Ikari Shinji-kun, your only hope lies with the two Spears left at the Impact epicenter in Dogma.
They are the key to activating Instrumentality.
All we have to do is obtain those Spears.
If we do that, Nerv will not be able to cause Fourth Impact.
And if we use them together with Eva-13, it becomes possible to fix the world.
I see...
Yes. It is possible for you.
It is possible WITH you.
Eva-13 uses a double entry system.
Let the two of us become the hope of the Lilin.
Because what you need the most right now is hope,
along with atonement and an open heart.
You're amazing. You know everything.
That's because I am always thinking about you.
Thank you, Nagisa-kun.
"Kaworu" is fine.
Ah, okay.
"Shinji" is fine for me, too.
It is the same as playing piano.
Good things will come if we do it together.
Let's go, Kaworu-kun.
Evangelion 13, start up!
Incoming signal!
Activation of a new type of Eva confirmed.
We're not alone.
You mean the Mark.09?
It's here as our backup.
It will warn us of any Wille activity.
The two of us should be enough for all that.
She isn't even Ayanami...
Not... Ayanami?
The walls...?
Yes, all failures of infinity.
Don't let them weigh upon your mind.
We're nearly at Lilith's barrier.
The Main Shaft is completely blocked,
keeping anyone from intruding over the past fourteen years.
It's like one big lid.
It's all right. Eva-13 was made for breaking through this.
The two of us can do it.
Try to join tempos.
Remember the piano duet.
Let's go, Shinji-kun.
We did it!
We've arrived. The deepest part of Central Dogma.
The epicenter of Third Impact.
Is this Lilith?
It once was.
Now, it is her corpse.
Misato-san, even though we tried to protect it with our lives...
Uh... That's an Eva?
Yes, the Eva Mark.06.
Remodeled into an autonomous type,
exploitation by the Lilin brought the unit to a state of ruin.
The things that are piercing them... are our targets?
Yes, the Spears of Longinus and Cassius.
Wielding both requires two souls.
That is why we have the double entry system.
Then... wouldn't that pilot have been just as good for this as me?
No, a Lilin imitation cannot be used.
Their souls' placement is different.
Well, let's begin.
Hold on.
Something is wrong.
What is it, Kaworu-kun?
This is not right...
Both of the Spears have changed to a similar shape.
Let's just pull the Spears quickly!
That's why we came here in this Eva.
What's going on?!
Eva-02?
Asuka!
What are you doing, Asuka?!
Stupid Shinji?!
You can't seriously be piloting an Eva?
I am.
I'm going to change the world with this Eva!
You little brat...
If that's how it is, don't pilot!
Support fire, you're always late!
Sorry, sorry!
Adams' Vessel-san,
the least I can do is get you to stick around.
Why are you interfering, Asuka?
Those are our Spears of Hope!
Stop!... looking!... for trouble!
You brat, Shinji!
Are you planning to start Third Impact again?
You're wrong!
I'm trying to fix everything!
I'm trying to save the world!
You really are a little twerp.
You just don't get it!
Kaworu-kun, why aren't you helping?
Cassius and Longinus. Both of the Spears are needed...
But the only two Spears that are here are the same...
Kaworu-kun!
That's it!
Now I understand,
Lilin!
Hey, Ms. Sucks To Be Seele's Pilot,
you can hear me, right?
Don't you think you should get out before you turn into an Adams' Vessel?
No. That is not the order I received.
Talk about a square.
You know your original was a whole lot more friendly?
Original?
The other me...
Kaworu-kun? What's the matter?
Asuka...
Please! Stay out of our way!
Go down quietly, you little brat!
Of all times!
Hey, Glasses! I need a spare!
While we still have the chance! The Spears!
You'd raise a hand against a girl...
You're the worst.
Spare, incoming!
Let's stop, Shinji-kun.
I have a bad feeling about this...
We can't, Kaworu-kun!
We came here to do something!
We've done enough!
These aren't the Spears we came for!
Not... the Spears we came for...
You're the one who said we need the Spears.
That's why I got into this Eva!
The control system...?
For Kaworu-kun,
for everyone, I will get the Spears!
Only then will the world go back to the way it should be.
If I do that, even Misato-san will...
Damn!
Glasses! Get rid of the barrier!
You're cleared to use AA ammo!
I've been waiting for this.
Check these babies out!
No A.T. Field?
Don't tell me this unit...
Don't do it, Shinji-kun!
Stop, you stupid brat!
Let's begin, Fuyutsuki.
Eva Mark.06?
Pattern blue?
What's going on?
This is bad!
The 12th Angel is still alive!
Glasses, Container No.3!
Got it!
I'll deal with this before Third Impact starts up again!
It was on orders.
An Angel?!
Princess, you should cease the futile fire.
The whole thing is a core.
With just us, there's no way to hurt it.
Besides that, by defeating the Last Angel,
we don't know what kind of evil will come out.
You're worried, no?
This is...
This is... me?
What am I...?
The controls aren't responding.
What's going on, Kaworu-kun?
Kaworu-kun!
I never imagined that I, the First Angel,
would be cast down to the 13th.
What are you doing, Kaworu-kun?
So the beginning and the end are the same.
I'd expected as much from the King of the Lilin,
Shinji-kun's father!
DSS Choker, pattern blue?
A thirteenth? Even though the 12th should've been the last?!
So this is what Gendo-kun is aiming for.
It is time to amend the Dead Sea Scrolls' contract.
This is farewell.
Even though all of you have changed the shape of your souls,
you are still lifeforms blessed with the Fruit of Knowledge.
You were able to live for eternity,
but, same as us, you still cannot escape the fate of death.
To advance the evolution of the flock burdened with death,
you had bestowed upon us the gift of civilization.
As the representative of humanity, I say thank you.
Through death, I shall return your souls to where they belong.
The long desired Human Instrumentality Project,
and the contracted deicide, will be completed by me.
Rest assured.
Our wishes have come to fruition.
Good.
Everything is good.
Human Instrumentality.
We hope for the peaceful purification of all souls.
Damn it!
It's entering its pseudo-evolved form!
Guess it's Awakening...
It's a surviving Adams!
What's this...?
What IS this...?
It's all my fault!
Because I pulled the Spears!
This is...!
Fourth Impact...
These are the opening ceremonies.
Kaworu-kun...
The choker!
Misato-san?!
A.T. Field at maximum!
Contain the Eva in its present state!
Prepare the main armaments for a salvo! Load the mortar shells!
Do whatever it takes to keep Fourth Impact in check!
Fire!
Damage received! Direct hit to main armament!
The Adams' Vessel?!
Shots received on midsection! Damage unknown!
/ The target is the new-type Eva! ####
Rudder is ineffective!
We're losing altitude!
/ ?######!
The Adams' Vessel... Wunder's original master!
It intends to take the ship's controls back from Eva-01!
Why can't I restore the link?
Oh, man!
These guys are not messing around.
Glasses, you handle the brat's Eva!
I'll help out Wunder with 02'!
Roger!
Unable to reject the Adams' Vessel!
Unidentified data is infiltrating the main control system!
It's hijacking control of the ship!
Talk about cheap! That's Seele's style, all right.
Mode change!
Code 777!
Who's there?
Who the hell are YOU?!
Report from lower bridge.
Eva-02' has engaged the Adams' Vessel!
We're counting on you, Asuka.
If I were Ayanami Rei, what would I do at a time like this?
Hell if I know!
Do whatever you want!
And now, for the core!
Geez! The whole thing's a core?
No time...
Sorry, Eva-02!
Control systems restored!
Emergency launch of all ships!
Pursue the target Eva immediately!
Captain, it won't be possible until the main unit is restored!
Shinji-kun...
This is all because of me...
I...
It's not your fault.
It's because I became the Thirteenth Angel.
I'm the trigger.
What do I do?
Hey, what are we going to do?
Kaworu-kun,
tell me what the right thing would be.
Even if souls disappear, hopes and curses will remain in this world.
Intent is imparted to the world as information and goes on to change.
In time, even one's very self is being rewritten.
I'm sorry. This isn't the happiness you wished for.
I will close the Door of Guf.
You don't need to worry about it, Shinji-kun.
Kaworu-kun...
What are you saying, Kaworu-kun?
I don't get any of it!
Shinji-kun, you should find a place of peace and self.
Fate will surely guide you.
Don't make that face.
We'll meet again, Shinji-kun.
Kaworu-kun!
The Door of Guf hasn't closed yet?
So, Puppy Boy is Seele's backup measure!
I'm done cleaning up!
Hang in there, Puppy Boy!
Don't be such a baby!
Help out the Princess, at least!
Be a man!
And while you're at it, get to know the world a little!
What a nightmare.
Nearly all went as Seele intended.
But not only was Seele's boy eliminated, the path was forged for Eva-13's Awakening.
Captain Katsuragi's actions are within predictions, as well.
This will do for now.
All ships, maintain organization for Class 2 withdrawal.
No pattern blue readings.
No ships sighted in withdrawal airspace.
Damaged areas of the midsection have received emergency treatment.
Fourth Impact was stopped, but we don't know whom to thank.
/ #?????##?????
/ ????????????????####?
Misato, let's leave it for now...
You brat, Shinji.
You didn't come to help me?
Yet again, it's all about you.
You think you can just get away with what's happened by not saying a thing.
You still need pampering?
No matter how much time passes... you're always such a brat!
Here, put this on.
Jeez! You can stand on your own, can't you?!
You're the pilot from before.
From an early lot of Ayanami Types, are you?
The L Barrier's density is too strong here, so they won't come to help us.
We're going to where the Lilin are.
Come on!
Preview
Shinji Ikari continues to wander, still lacking the will to live.
He reaches a place where he learns hope.
Finally the Instrumentality Project is set in motion.
To prevent Final Impact,
Wille make one last grueling stand.
Wunder tears through the skies!
Eva Unit 8+2 races across the red earth!
Next time in "New Evangelion Theatrical Edition".
New Evangelion Theatrical Edition: ||
There'll be fan service all the way up to the end!